It is the most famous, most expensive
and most mysterious painting in the
world.
Each year, millions of people visit the
portrait in the Louvrea.
The Mona Lisa has remained a star among
works of art for centuries.
Because fanatics attempted to destroy
the painting, it can now only be admired
from behind armored glass.
But what makes a Mona Lisa so special?
The small painting shows nothing more
than a portrait of a woman.
Or does it reveal something more?
>> [music]
>> It was painted by one of the greatest
geniuses who ever lived, Leonardo da
Vinci. And with Mona Lisa, he left
behind more than just an image of a
woman.
Her
gaze appears to wander off, yet always
meets the viewer.
She wears no jewelry. Her clothing is
dark as if she were in mourning, [music]
and yet she smiles mysteriously.
Leonardo didn't leave behind any
sketches of the portrait.
No visible brush strokes. Mona Lisa
appears to be made out of flesh and
blood.
Yet her biggest secret remains. Who was
she? Whose portrait is Leonardo showing
us?
To solve this puzzle, the louver placed
its most famous painting under
scientific scrutiny using the most
modern techniques.
The painting was examined using X-rays,
ramen spectroscopy,
ultraviolet and infrared pictures among
other techniques to uncover its secrets.
The master's painting technique was
examined [music] beyond the surface.
Were corrections made to the painting?
Was anything overpainted?
Did Leonardo paint the piece in one
session or did he work on it for [music]
decades?
These questions must be answered [music]
in order to resolve the most puzzling
question of them all. Who is the woman
behind the smiling yet melancholy face?
Who was Leonardo's Mona Lisa?
Or is this not a portrait, but rather an
imaginary image of an ideal beauty?
[music]
Experts have been wondering this for
centuries.
There seems to be proof of only two
explanations,
but each cancels the other out.
documentation comes from two different
chronicers, but these written [music]
records are not compatible with one
another.
The [music] most accepted theory is
based on biographer Georgio Vasari.
According to him, the portrait depicts
Lisa Deljacondo,
the wife of the Florentine silk merchant
Francesco Deljacondo, who commissioned
the piece in 1503.
This contradicts a note by the
chronicler Antonio deiatis [music] from
in which Leonardo da Vinci claims to
have been commissioned by Giuliano de
Medici.
[music]
Just like the two chronicers,
contemporary Leonardo scholars also have
divergent theories.
Jeppi Palanti, an art historian from
Florence, believes the officially
recognized theory that the painting
depicts Lisa deljondo.
>> I believe that Leonardo actually painted
Lisa Gardini, the wife of Franchesco del
Jondor,
probably around 1503.
to three.
>> Roman historian Roberto Taperi considers
a new and revolutionary theory in which
the portrayed woman is an entirely
different person.
>> I think the painting is connected with
Brandani.
>> It has nothing to do with Mona Lisa.
>> The first clue leads to Florence. The
majority of the great Renaissance
artists lived and worked here as did
Leonardo da Vinci.
Giorgio Vasari also worked in Florence.
He chronicled the biographies of many
Italian artists. [music]
Visari wasn't just anybody. Next to his
occupation as a chronicler, he was also
a painter and an architect.
He planned Florence's largest and most
important buildings, including the
Aitzy.
The building complex was [music]
originally designed to house ministries
and public offices, but its original
purpose soon changed.
The Fitzy became the home to one of the
most significant art collections in the
world.
Some of Leonardo's paintings are also
exhibited [music] here today, such as
his early piece, Annunciation,
in which his love for detail [music] is
already discernible.
[music]
Visari also built something unique to
Florence [music] that remains concealed
from many people. A connecting walkway
underneath the city's [music] roofs. It
leads from the Palato Veio through the
Offitzy and crosses the Ponttovecio.
With it, Florence's elite could wander
across the city without coming into
contact [music] with the commoners on
the street.
The path ends in the garden of Palazzo
Pitti.
Next to his work as an architect, Vasari
documented the biographies of great
Italian artists. Today, these make up
one of the most important foundations of
art history.
Levite de Pure Chilenti Architecti
Ptoriali
was first published in 1550 and revised
in 1568.
Today the original manuscripts are
housed in the Aitzy library.
Most of the artists whose lives Visari
chronicled were already dead at the
time, but Visari researched very
carefully.
So too with Leonardo da Vinci on just a
few pages, Visari wrote down his whole
life story.
In it, he also mentions that Leonardo
painted the portrait of Mona Lisa for
Francesco de Jakondo, her husband, and
it's in the possession of King Francis I
of France.
He labored on it for 4 years and
ultimately left it unfinished.
These words gave the painting its name.
Mona Lisa. [music]
Who was this Mona Lisa of whom Vasari
wrote? And who was her husband?
Francesco Deljacondo.
Francesco was a silk merchant who had
[music] acquired some wealth but wasn't
part of Florence's elite.
He was a nuvo ree businessman.
Was it [music] really possible that a
renowned painter like Leonardo accepted
a commission by an ordinary businessman?
Or did Franchesco Deljando [music]
and his wife climb the ranks of society?
Franchesco.
>> Franchesco del Jakondo was well known in
the city.
He wasn't just an ordinary merchant. He
was also a public and [music]
charismatic figure.
Lisa was very young and Vasari defines
her as very beautiful too.
Her husband also spoke very highly of
her.
In his testament, Francesco refers to
her as a bonafided woman.
This is an unusual description for a
woman.
I have yet to find a similar description
in other testaments.
A bonafided woman can signify a noble
woman with high principles who works
hard and has personality.
[music]
Lisa Del Jacondo was Franchesco's third
wife.
The birth of their second child and move
into a new home could have been the
occasion for the commissioned portrait.
And yet up until then, Leonardo only
portrayed men and women of [music]
nobility. These people were interesting
to him. A star such as himself [music]
could choose his own subjects. Why did
he paint Lisa Deljondo?
At the time, the city of Florence was
considered a metropolis. Yet, a specific
circumstance could have brought Leonardo
and Francesco together.
Pierro da Vinci lived near Franchesco.
He was one of the most influential
notaries in Florence and Leonardo's
father.
Francesco had a reputation as a user and
he was often in court. For this and
other business affairs, he needed a
notary.
>> Without question, there was no close
connection between Jakondo's family and
Leonardos.
A document from 1496 confirms the visits
and personal connection between the
notary and father of Dainci San Pierro
and Francesco Deljokond.
Franchesco San Pier recorded an
agreement between Franchesco Deljond and
the monks of the Santisima Anutiata
Abbey inside the Florentine merchants
own store.
This signifies that Franchesco was most
certainly a client of San Pierro near
the end of the 15th century.
>> Leonardo returned to Florence around
1500 from Milan. He was 48 years old,
restless, without family, and didn't
have any large commissions on the
horizon.
Leonardo. When Leonardo came to
Florence, he didn't have any commissions
or work.
And we know that portraits are the bread
and butter of painters.
That is to say, they are the simplest
commissions and also the best paid. So,
it is easily possible that Francesco
Deljando commissioned Leonardo to
portray his wife. did.
>> It's possible that Leonardo's father
introduced them to one another and that
Jakando used the opportunity to
commission a portrait of his wife from
the great master.
But doubts arise. The Jacondo family
trade register resides in the Livio
Storic del Instituto delinoenti
and it is the basis of their tax [music]
report.
Florence had a highly advanced [music]
tax system, the so-called catastro.
As part of this, its citizens had to
claim all of their incomes and
expenditures. [music]
In this trade register, all movement of
money and assets were meticulously
recorded.
Visari mentions that Leonardo received
the commission in 1503, so a record of
the expensive [music] portrait must
certainly have been made.
But in 1503
there is no reference to the expense of
a painting.
There is no record of a commission to
Leonardo in the entire trade register.
There is also no mention of such a
valuable painting in the inheritance.
[music]
>> You can imagine how desperately I
searched for clues of a commission or
payment.
Not even in the testament is there
mention that this painting existed.
I think Francesco would have certainly
claimed it since it was a painting with
a rising and secure value. The whole
thing is incomprehensible.
Franchesco would have most likely shown
the portrait by the famous painter
publicly and would not have risked
eventual tax evasion. In Leonardo's
records, there is also no trace of a
commission by Franchesco.
Money apparently didn't change hands.
Franchesco's testament is archived in
Florence's Archivio Dist. Therein there
is also no mention of the great master's
valuable artwork.
Leonardo apparently never delivered the
painting to Franchesco. [music]
Visari writes about an incomplete
portrait. The Mona Lisa in the Loura,
however, is completed down to the very
last detail.
>> Yes, surely he accepted the commission
at a time in which he had no work.
He introduced himself to the merchant
who wanted a painting of his wife and
simply agreed. Then he painted only the
head.
He interrupted the work for other
commissions and left it unfinished.
Never delivering the painting to the
merchant, not even the head.
There are no traces of this painting in
Florence. Traces left by the merchant
couple must be available in the
archives, in documents or testaments.
And yet this painting by Leonardo shows
up nowhere.
If he had finished the painting and
delivered it, then a record within the
family would exist. A painting by a
famous artist like Leonardo was a very
valuable commodity.
It had disappeared. We know absolutely
nothing about it. [music]
Has
it really been lost? [music] Was the
Mona Lisa as described by Vasari lost?
Is the painting in the Loura a different
one?
Many of Da Vinci's works have been lost.
Mona Lisa wouldn't be an exception. Some
however have reemerged unexpectedly
>> in the art world there are rigid
unwritten laws.
>> One such law states that no new
Leonardos may surface
looks is an art restorer in Vienna.
He was commissioned to restore a small
and worthless copy of the famous
Leonardo painting, Virgin of the Rocks.
>> The owner of the copy wasn't concerned
with its value since the painting was de
facto, not worth very much. The subject
was clear. It is the Virgin of the
Rocks, and the presumption that it was a
small copy of the famous Virgin of the
Rocks in the Louvre was completely
valid. The painting had damage that I
was to repair.
>> Looks took a closer look at the small
painting. First, he determined the type
of color pigments used with a Roman
spectroscope.
He determined that a special lead tin
yellow was used that hadn't been in use
since 1720.
During Leonardo's time, making colors
was very complex.
They weren't manufactured synthetically,
but came from nature. They were either
made up of organic material or of metals
and minerals.
These colors were especially expensive.
They had to be ground into tiny granules
and then bound with a binding agent.
Today, these are immediately detectable
and make it easy to identify
counterfeits.
After looks discerned that the colors
used matched up with Leonardo's time,
[music] he went on to more accurately
determine the work's age. To do so, he
used the radiocarbon dating method, and
the result was sensational.
The small painting actually stemmed from
Leonardo's time, but he wasn't satisfied
yet. With the help of infrared pictures,
looks penetrated the surface to the
first layer of paint. Often times
painters make sketches with charcoal
before introducing oils.
This painting also contained a charcoal
sketch and it had been modified and
corrected.
It appeared that first someone had
searched for the right composition.
Only the artist himself would have done
such a thing.
In this case, Leonardo.
My first reaction was disbelief. I
thought this must be a mistake.
Infrared and X-rays are imaging methods
that leave a lot of room for
interpretation and are often over relied
upon.
>> But more and more preliminary sketches
surfaced. Looks documented the
variations and his verdict gained
substance. This artist drafted a
preliminary sketch in search of the
right composition.
And this artist can only have been
Leonardo himself.
>> I slowly felt the adrenaline rush.
I searched for an explanation.
It can't be Leonardo
because it is forbidden for it to be
from him.
What else could it be? If not by him, by
whom else? What is the explanation for
this phenomenon?
>> It was the only possible interpretation
left. It must have been by Leonardo.
It's the only way that all the different
pieces of evidence fit together.
Much about Leonardo seems unexplainable
[music]
today. Very few artists have captivated
people's imaginations [music] as he has.
One reason for this is that he started
so many paintings that he never finished
like that of St. Jerome in the
wilderness.
Yet these works count among art
history's most famous.
As with the adoration of the magi,
Leonardo often lost interest in his
paintings after he solved challenges of
figuration and composition. Finishing
the pieces became too tedious.
This was also the case with the fresco
for the council hall of Palato Veio.
It was to become his largest work.
Commissioned by the city government,
Leonardo chose the battle of Angiari as
his motif.
Leonardo received the commission in
1503, the same period during which he
worked on Lisa Deljacond's [music]
portrait.
Restless as he was, Leonardo left even
the biggest project that Florence
commissioned incomplete.
Is it plausible that he behaved
similarly with Mona Lisa, abandoning it
only to finish it later?
The answer lies north of the Alps at the
University of H Highleberg in Germany.
In its library are early printed works,
so-called incunables from the 15th
century.
Sabina Gerine is an expert of these
books. In one of these incunables,
Leonardo's contemporary Agugustino
Vespuchi left a remarkable note.
>> In the process of a systematic and
scientific survey of all the incunables
at our university library, we came
across Vespuchi's notes in this Cicero
incunable. And this was a small
sensation.
We found the name Leonardo da Vinci, the
name Lisa Deljacondo and this accidental
discovery turned out to be significant
for Leonardo and Mona Lisa scholarship.
>> After Leonardo received the commission
for the battle of Angiari, Basbuchi
visited him in his studio and about this
he wrote the following. The painter
appelis Leonardo da Vinci proceeds like
him in all of his paintings. For
example, the portrait of Lisa deljacondo
and Anna the Virgin's mother. We will
see what he will make of the Grand
Council Hall that he's just agreed to do
with a Gonfalainer.
October 1503.
Vaspuchcci assumes that Leonardo will do
what a pelis [music] a famous painter of
antiquity did with his works. leave the
portrait of Lisa and the battle of
Angiari incomplete.
With this note, a contemporary of
Leonardo's confirms the commission to
paint the portrait of Mona Lisa.
This discovery naturally supports
Visari's theory that [music] the
painting which we all admire as the Mona
Lisa in the Loura today is of Lisa
Deljacondo, the wife of a Florentine
merchant and that the painting was not
yet completed in October of 153.
>> It is very likely that Leonardo put the
painting aside.
He didn't finish it and never delivered
it. It was most likely completed at a
later time.
So I think that this theory in which the
painting was begun in 1503
and finished later is the most plausible
and it's also the one I personally
believe in.
When did Leonardo finish the painting?
Let's assume in old age, long after he
started it.
Then Leonardo must have carried the
painting with him throughout much of his
life.
If there was such a time span between
the start and the completion of the
painting, then we can determine [music]
that with today's modern methods.
And again, modern technology has a go at
the Mona Lisa.
The results show that the color pigments
were applied without significant
interruption.
Using infrared technology, historians
searched for overpainted areas or
corrections.
The genius Leonardo made hardly a single
correction from the first brush stroke
to the finished piece.
The only overpainting occurred on Mona
Lisa's left hand. Here, Leonardo
corrected the gesture of her finger.
Aside from that, the painting was made
in one session. An unbelievable
achievement by the master.
According to art historian Alexander
Perig, these discoveries further
confound the Mona Lisa theory.
The entire study confirms the absurdity
of the identity of the louver painting
or louver painting depicting Mona Lisa.
was fairly continuous.
He would have had to paint it in two
completely separate stages
which would clearly be identified with
today's methods and tools.
The landscape would have had to have
been new since Versari didn't mention
one at all.
[music]
>> The great biographer heirs in another
aspect as well.
In describing the Mona Lisa, he talks
about her eyelashes which could be
rendered only by the most delicate of
brushes. on her brows. You witness them
at their fullest and sparest, and how
they emerge from the pores of her skin
and arch as naturally as one can only
imagine.
But the Mona Lisa that hangs in the
Loura today has neither eyelashes nor
eyebrows.
These are also not detectable using
relief imaging.
Visari, one of the main attesters to the
Mona Lisa theory, never saw the painting
himself.
>> Visari didn't have any written sources.
His biography is based on mere oral
accounts that circulated in Florence.
This means he wrote part of the history
of Duk's portrait.
The Mona Lisa based on such oral
accounts that passed from person to
person.
He himself never saw the painting.
He described what he invented.
But from where does [music] the painting
in the louver stem? Are there two
portraits, one of them lost?
This new [music] idea takes us to the
ammois on the Lir France.
Leonardo died here in 1519 at the
advanced [music] age of 67.
The chapel in which he was intombed is
located directly next to the king's
[music] chateau.
Leonardo came to Amboir [music] by
invitation of the French king Francis I.
By then the artistic [music] genius had
already achieved cult status.
[music]
Leonardo lived in a manor next to the
chateau called Clo Luc.
An incident occurred in this small
French manner that steers the Mona Lisa
investigation in an entirely new and
revolutionary direction.
>> Leonardo brought three paintings with
him. the one that today is referred to
as the Mona Lisa, the painting of St.
John the Baptist and that of St. Anne.
>> He stayed in this manner in Clus where
he also had his studio.
The chronicler Antonio Deiatis [music]
witnessed Cardinal Ludvig of Aragan's
visit with Leonardo in Klo Luc on
October the 10th, 1517.
He relates the three paintings he saw at
the aging masters.
One of the works is of a certain
Florentine lady painted from life that
was made in honor of the passing of
Juliano de Medici. Another one is of the
young St. Joan the Baptist, the third of
Madonna with her child seated on St.
Anna's lap. The latter was the most
perfect of them all.
Today the painting of St. Anna with
Maria and baby Jesus on her lap is
housed in the Louvrea.
So too is the painting that Beatatis
described of St. John the Baptist
is the painting that was made for
Juliano de Medici also in the Loura.
Is it the Mona Lisa?
>> The painting was commissioned in Rome by
Juliano Deichi
as a result of an affair he had with a
woman from
Juliano
Brandani.
Pacifica brandani.
[music]
A new name surfaces. [music]
Medi,
the ruling family of Florence. This name
is most associated with the Renaissance
period. They were rich, scrupulous,
obsessed [music] with power, and patrons
of the arts.
>> [music]
>> Juliano Demedichi was one of the two
brothers that lived during Da Vinci's
time.
He was a womanizer and a squander.
He was charismatic, had a powerful name
and an influential brother.
His
[music]
brother lived in Rome. His name was
Givani de Medici and he had high
aspirations.
Later he became cardinal and finally
pope. As Pope Leo I 10th he made history
as a sensitive art patron as well as a
scrupulous and powerful politician.
He strengthened the clergy's power and
influence over the battling Italian
citystates and had a weakness for the
beautiful things in life.
Juliano, his extravagant brother,
arrived in Orbino, where he was a guest
at the Palazzo Ducala.
Here he had several [music] chambers
known as the Magnificence Quarter.
[music]
>> Julano was a poet. He had been raised by
his father, Lorenzo, who was a great
writer. He wrote poetry and was
interested in women. He hadn't the
slightest interest in politics. [music]
Leone his brother was a great
politician. The exact opposite.
He was wrong about everything. And yet
his great passion was politics.
He was an avid hunter,
>> but then a politician.
Giovanni Deerichi. Pope Leo I 10th took
care of his brother Giuliano throughout
his life. He also financed his
extravagant lifestyle.
Juliano had countless affairs,
but one of these flings had serious
consequences.
Obino in the Mara [music] region. The
Palazzo Dala looms over the town. Here
the tragedy involving Juliano Deerichi
that would eventually lead to the Mona
Lisa took place.
The most important source is a document
that is housed in the library of the
University of Obino. This document is a
page in a book of foundlings.
Records were found in the university
library of Obino regarding a certain
Hippolto de Medici.
Hippolto would later become cardinal but
was poisoned at the age of 24.
But he was born an orphan.
How did he acquire the name Medi?
Who were his parents?
Further records document his birth, how
he became an orphan, and later a Medii.
The name of his mother also appears.
Pacifica Brandani, a young woman from
Obino.
Not much is known about Pacifica
Brandani. She was a guest to the Pala
Ducala by invitation of Juliano
Deirichi.
>> [music]
>> It is unclear if she offered him her
labors of love, if he seduced her, or as
recorded by one of the documents was
raped.
In any case, she spent a night with
Juliano.
and this likely involuntarily.
But how should she have opposed the rich
ruler? [music]
[music]
She was plagued with severe remorse
after her affair with Juliano.
Some sources state that she was married
at the time.
Brandani fell into a crisis that [music]
deepened when she found out that she was
with child.
A child out of wedlock from a brief
[music] encounter in the court of Obino.
Then she drew up a terrible plan.
She confided in her friend and midwife
that she didn't want the child and that
she could not take the disgrace.
The midwife should kill the newborn in
case Pandani dies in childbirth.
Brandani did in fact die of pure pro
fever,
but the midwife didn't take the [music]
newborn's life.
On April the 19th, 1511, the night
before Easter Sunday, she dropped the
child off on the steps of the Santa
Kiara church in Urbino.
The baby wrapped in a white sheet was
Giuliano's son. He had a coin on him as
a token of his heritage.
In the absence of a legitimate heir,
Julian de Medici recognized him as his
son. He named him Apolto.
>> Juliano left Obino with his son Apolto.
A move to his brother, the Pope, in
Rome.
Leonardo da Vinci resided in the
chambers of the Vatican where he worked
for the Medici during this time.
But commissions from the pope were
sparse. Here Giuliano must have given
him the commission of which Leonardo
writes in Clus.
Leonardo was to paint a painting to
comfort little Epolito.
He said to Leonardo, "Paint me a picture
of a mother that I can gift to my son as
an image of his mother.
Paint it as you imagine it. How a
portrait of a mother should look like
and Leonardo painted the painting that
we call Mona today.
It must have been a great challenge to
paint an image of a mother for Apolto
since he suffered a similar fate as
Apolto.
He too was an illegitimate [music] child
who was recognized by his father. His
mother didn't [music] die in childbirth.
She was his father's maid, and he
probably used her dependency on him for
labors of love, as had Juliana with his
mistress, Brandani.
[music]
Apolitto and Leonardo shared a similar
[music] fate and this inspired Leonardo
to paint a painting that upheld the
memory of a mother.
The painting should lend comfort to
[music] young Apolito who himself never
saw his mother.
>> He undoubtedly painted [clears throat]
the image of a mother.
>> He developed the portrait out of his
imagination.
Leonardo didn't need a model.
>> He was an illegitimate child himself and
could easily relate to the feelings of
such a child.
>> Juliano de Medici must have known this
as Leonardo's friend. Leonardo,
Leonardo took himself [music] back to
the time of his childhood.
He was born in 1452 on a farm.
His birthhouse [music]
still stands today. It's located in
midst of an olive grove near the small
[music] Tuscan village of Vinci.
The great master got his name from the
small Italian village.
A church with a side chapel and a
baptistry stands in the center [music]
of town.
Leonardo was baptized here. A memorial
stone commemorates that illegitimate
Leonardo was recognized as a son by his
father, Pierro Dainci.
It was always puzzling why Leonardo
portrayed the wife of a silk merchant in
dark clothing. A silk merchant is proud
of his colorful fabrics. Her clothes, on
the other hand, recall mourning and
revery. If Leonardo painted the image of
[music] a woman that had passed away,
then the dark colors make sense. Her
smile also becomes explainable since it
is directed at her own child.
Juliano de Medici died before the
painting was completed.
Leonardo took it with him to France
where Deiatis saw it and took note of it
in his travel.
>> [music]
>> The painting in the louver is certainly
not identical to the portrait that
Leonardo painted of Mona Lisa
Mona, the real Mona Lisa,
Lisa Del Jondo,
the silk merchant's wife.
But where is the portrait of Lisa
Deljacondo as described by Vasari?
A trace leads us to Jan Jakamo Capoti
called Salai who is said to have had a
relationship with the master.
Salai was [music] a rap scallion, but
Leonardo liked him anyway.
He accompanied the master through his
life on many travels and was his studio
assistant. [music]
Leonardo several months or weeks before
Leonardo left for France in 1516,
[music]
Salai returned to his hometown of Milan.
On the occasion, he must have received
several paintings from Leonardo,
presumably incomplete works.
A painting appears in his estate that is
referred to as La Jand
Quadroto La Jakonda. A painting called
Jakonda. This is how it appears in his
estate.
An incomplete work of the great Leonardo
da Vinci was very valuable to Salai.
Theoretically, Salai could have
completed it, right?
He was a painter trained by Leonardo.
Many paintings are attributed to him.
He could have also sold them under
Leonardo's name for a lot of money.
But that never happened. Salai died
under mysterious circumstances just a
few years after Leonardo's own death.
The incomplete portrait of Lisa del
Jakando was in Salai's estate along with
Leonardo's painting Lea and the Swan.
Both of these paintings were lost.
In all likelihood, it is the imaginary
ideal image of a mother that hangs in
the Loura commissioned by Juliano
Demedi.
We must say goodbye to the Mona Lisa.
It is the most famous painting in the
world.
None other has been studied more
thoroughly or more often. Now the Mona
Lisa has revealed its true face.
The same face was found over and over
again beneath each of the coats of
paint. The face with its loving gaze and
its comforting smile. The image of a
mother
Heat.
[music]